All right, it's September 3rd, 2025.
This is active inference stream 15.1.
Been a little bit, but we're back. We're
in the start repo.
Start.active inference.institute.
And this should be a very fun multilevel
stream. Right off the bat, this is where
we're going to get through today. I'm
running run.sh from the top of the repo
and several functionalities are shown
which we're going to go through. The
first is the system checkup. The second
is an environment setup step. The third
is the generation of custom curriculum.
This is going to use LLM's generative AI
to write custom active inference
onboarding curricula depending on a
given audience or entity and then
translate that into whatever language
you want. And then the fourth option is
the repository manager where we will
clone into a variety of repos. So I am
going to get a few of those cooking.
Welcome this fine evening. Looking
forward to everyone's comments and
questions. First in this one I'm going
to get the repository cloning going.
Clone the available repositories
and get that going in the background.
Then I'm going to open up another
run.sh instance
slash
run
sh. On the second one, I'm going to
start up a custom curriculum generator.
As soon as somebody types in the live
chat a given entity that they'd like to
see, I'll add in another one as well.
So, let's get in there. We will go to
three generate curricula
initializing the epistemic and pragmatic
aspects of consciousness
connecting to the free energy principle.
Okay, here we go.
What this interactive curriculum
generator gives us is
uh some options, some interactive
options for what kind of domain we want
to do research into and what
audience we want to tailor the material
to and what language. So we'll start out
with either entering an existing domain
like physics or we can add a new domain.
This is going to be
um
coffee
tasting.
Yes, it's a new domain. Target entities.
We can pick a given entity. We'll go
with
Gabber just as the first listed entity
there.
And then we can pick a target language.
And we'll go with
ancient Greek.
Okay. It's a new language. That's fine.
All right. Coffee tasting Tulsi Gabbert
ancient Greek. Yes. Proceed with that.
Okay. While that's proceeding, check in
on the cloning. This is going into the
clones
subfolder under SRC.
and that is cloning into a variety of
repos. Some of which are explored in
other streams, others which I've made
some major updates to over the previous
few days. So we're going to look into
some in a little bit more detail, but
let's pull back to this agenda. So
again, welcome. This is the start/ year
a map and what might happen next.
There's a repo that goes along with
this.
Just expanded the browser window. This
repo is
at github.com/activeinference
institute
start
and
it is an advanced AI powered system for
creating personalized active imprints in
free energy principal curricula and more
and much more. It's also connected with
a documentation local and cloud hosted
documentation strategy. So active
inference institute.github.io/start
will give you some hosted documents
and also they will pop up locally and
some quick links are shown to run the
experience. You can do dot /run.sh.
That's what we did. Or let's open up
another window and use the other top
level run script which is dot / run
docs
dot slash run docs. So what that's going
to do
is run the document checking and
rendering
preparing any packages that are needed
along the way. And then pop up here in
the browser window is a locally rendered
at IP address 127.0.0.1
port 803. So this is the locally
implemented
server for documents
or you can look at the exact same
material in the GitHub document pages.
So we'll keep that in mind and we'll
kill the dock runner.
Okay.
Just crashed.
Okay, we're back.
Okay,
we're back.
All right,
so
we're live in the stream. I look forward
to anyone's comments. And let's just go
over what is going to happen first. What
is the start here repo? Well, this is
just to get it out in an infant stream
and show a little bit of the behind the
scenes. But this repo, broadly speaking,
gives an interactive and well-linging
page into the active inference ecosystem
and institute. Now elsewhere we have
some
welcome page that has a lot more
interactive material and a lot of
hyperlinks to our our living document.
But
there isn't any code execution in KOD.
So what I've been working on is this
start repo which has a little bit more
of a seamless experience in terms of not
just linking to resources but actually
making a repo that runs them. So this
repo gives a fun interactive
matrix themed uh landing page into the
institute and ecosystem. It renders as
we've seen into local documentation as
well as updated GitHub pages. It uses
generative AI to write custom
curriculum. We'll see if that will
worked. That looks like it's still
going.
And it also helps us clone and deploy
repositories. So for example, what we
have cloned while that was all happening
is active inference.jl JL which I have
made a fork and some modifications to
Axiom which is the recent open- source
architecture by Versus Cerebrum which is
the linguistic approach to modeling case
systems and other linguistic aspects in
models. the cognitive repo which is a
large underlying obsidian formatted
markdown knowledge repository that you
can open up with foam or in
obsidian
generalized notation notation GNN for
notation and meta programming with
generative models lean niche which has
been a bit of a fun collaboration with
Jason Larkin and we've been using the
lean theorem prover to explore a few
aspects of probabilistic dynamical
systems and the FEP pyomd which I've
made some heavy modifications to that
we'll go through RX infer examples also
a fork of which I've heavily modified
and template repo which is a repo for
setting up a scientific paper rendering
pipeline involving code and figures and
equations and all that. So this is just
an example. You can add more repos that
get cloned in, but start is hosting all
of these different repositories as
options to download in. So those repos
just mentioned and and many other
implementations exist
can help bring together open-source
implementation type frameworks like PVP,
active.jl, rx infer.jl, axiom, etc. and
all kinds of emerging tools be they
related to synthetic intelligence, LLM,
etc. And also anything that you want to
bring in in terms of adding in another
custom repo or just having another repo
in this clones folder, Attack of the
Clones. So
that is a cool setup landing page
Nexus. There's a few themes and ideas
that I think we'll revisit.
But what I will do next is
look at these themes, get a first pass
on the themes. Then we will look at some
of this custom generated curriculum
material. Then we will turn to the PIMDP
and active.jl
forks where I have made the most of the
modifications. So themes and ideas start
here now or act and first surf whatever
you prefer. Just jumping in. Active is
about action and perception. It's about
inbound outbound about joint
distributions for agents and niche grip
or gripped duck rabbit. All this kind of
stuff that we're always talking about.
And in our own learning and application
and contribution journeys, we just start
here now or there now or then if that's
a better when. But it is about doing. It
is about starting where and how you are.
Not waiting for something else to be the
case. Unless that's where and how you
are. Carographic pluralism. The name of
the stream is a map, not the map. It is
a map. It's not the only map. It's going
to version even during this stream and
also cardioraphic realism, cognitive
realism,
open- source intelligence, ecosystems,
and we're talking about ecosystems that
are we're mapping the ecosystem in terms
of sharing links and resources and
signposts. So, we're mapping the
ecosystem
of maps of mines
like mice, people, ant colonies, LLM
that map minds or not. Might might map
another mind there or it could just map
something.
We're mapping the ecosystem
of maps of minds, generative models that
do mapping.
There are multiple implementation
frameworks for active inference. There
are many ways to build up along the low
road.
We see that just by the juxtaposition of
all of these implementation frameworks
right here. And with GNN, we'll even
have each of them implementing where
possible some of the exact same models
and state spaces. So even for a given
state space there might be one or more
accessible ways to implement it with
different trade-offs. So implementations
do not negate each other in active
inference.
shipping the docks and docking the
shipment. Whether we approach this from
a vibe coding or a kind of uh
developer perspective or just the
relationship between making sure that
we're documented all along the way and
documenting what we ship and shipping
the docs. and this idea of notes to
navigation and the ways to include the
things that we're noting along the way
in our fieldwork and get through some
really dense sites in
one sitting. Okay,
we clone the repos. Let's close that
window.
All right,
let's exit the matrix.
So the generated content there is in the
learning
data.
So the domain research
here's the coffee tasting research that
was using perplexity.
I will push this to
GitHub just so we can look at this a
little bit
in a rendered form.
data.
Here was Infrance stream 8.1. That was
from December 15th, 2024. And that was
uh
oh it was uh 8.1 symbols greetings and
that was the first iteration of the
start repo.
Okay so here's the audience research.
Here's Tulsi Gabbard.
We also have that domain research with
the coffee tasting research.
And then here's the written curriculum.
Here's the Tulsi Gabbard curriculum.
Here's the complete complete Tulsi
curriculum.
So, it includes a little bit of
information on the person's background,
their motivation, what kinds of core
materials we're going to share with
them, what kinds of assessments, how to
connect it to the person's background.
So this is just a starting point for of
course that person or for any person or
for the system that generates it, but it
gives some really fun and exciting
starting points. So let's see a little
William Blake
background. Again, it's to be discussed,
explored, played with. How much do you
want to meet William Blake where he's at
versus just have a sort of
um attractor that isn't personalized.
So, it's not that there's a Oh, wow.
Look at this. Look at this gibberish
part.
Incredible.
Um it
and uh then we have the translations.
So that is in translated curriculum.
It looks like the the translation stage
is pretty slow. I didn't run it by
default, but we can see that there's
these translations of coffee roasting
and the so on. Okay,
here
we go. Starting to look a little bit at
the uh live chats by way of
still writing the uh
still writing some of the material.
Okay.
So,
let's go to some of the live chats.
Okay.
So, Dean, hello Dean.
wrote, "I have no technical background
with any of these repos, but I do want
to take advantage of the curriculum
generator. What's my first step? Do I
need to learn have priors with active?"
No, you don't need to have priors with
active.
You need to have it just this is this
starting point. Clone this repo start.
Find out from help or AI or videos how
to use GitHub. Clone the repo. Go to the
environment example
file. Copy it into a file called env
that just then add in in the real env
which is your secret file. Add in the
API keys for at least perplexity and
open router.
Then
top level of the repo
dot slash
run.sh.
This is going to go through the setup
phase. These this is not a loading
screen. I we can put we can put
different custom messages there.
I wouldn't say it's overly dramatic.
Okay. Then when it pops up here we are
in that interactive terminal
three generate curricula.
So we'll just get this
uh chugging along because it's it'll
take a little bit in the background
while we address the other one of your
comments and look at some of the repos
themselves. Okay. Select domain. Let's
do
islands
navigation using boats.
Yes. New domain target entity. This is
it could be skipped or you can come up
with another entity.
Um
I'll do Bill Gates.
created us a new entity
uh employee at Microsoft
and
we'll just call him a common character
target language and here we'll do
ancient Latin.
Yes, create that new one. Proceed. All
right. So that's all that takes and a
little bit of time to generate a new
curriculum
and this is just the version that we
have today. So future versions you can
imagine a a graphical interface or um
we can even make that right now.
So here add another script
in this folder
called
generate
curriculum GUI
which pops up a simple
browser window
with the same fields and information
as the interactive terminal one
yielding a query for
custom active inference
curriculum generation.
And then while it is working, it says
working with status bar estimate.
And then when final results are ready,
it
shows them
in gooey.
Thanks GPT5.
All right. So, we have the Bill Gates
curriculum developing in the background.
And meanwhile, I'm going to quickly
review the a few of these forks of
cloned repos that I've been working on
over the last few days. And we'll keep
an eye out on anyone's comments,
questions, live chat. All right, so here
we go.
The uh well, there's several interesting
ones. They're all very interesting, but
I want to show mainly the PIMDP. So,
this is all within this PIMDP fork and
just to show where this is in the
browser.
This is the
doxology. So my personal GitHub account
fork of PIMDP
and the branch
is called textbook.
So all that information is is open
source available. Okay. But here we'll
look at it through the interface of star
opened up in cursor and we are in cursor
1.59.
Okay. So couple of modifications and
things in this textbook. Uh first is the
examples from pmdp
which is just a copy over from the
examples
like the agent demo and grid world.
copying them over in their most minimal
form. And then the examples from PIMDP
modified, which is where uh modified
versions of the scripts are made that
output more data and more visualizations
than the uh notebook forms do.
So if you want to and the output of all
of the
scripts are run there. So purely just
for getting a better handle on the PIMDP
examples
and to to understand what they look
like.
uh that examples from PIMDP modified is
pretty cool, pretty useful, very open to
further developments that people can do
in of course the PIMDP examples in the
underlying repo or their own forks or
improving and making these examples more
flexible. But the examples, so just
examples is where I have made 12 new
examples. They get run by this script
called run all. So run all.sh
will run these 12 scripts. And here are
the outputs. So this is about to be like
a rapid review kind of like the 2022
paradol textbook that brings together
the fundamentals of probability and the
b rule in module 1 and two. Then module
3, 4, 5 and 6 are related to sensemaking
and perception.
Module 7, 8 and 9 are about active
inference, policy inference. And then
examples 10, 11, 12 are relating to the
POMDP, the partially observable marov
decision process. So here's what the
outputs look like. Starting from one,
probability basics. This is going to
talk about a few different distribution
types. So here's a categorical
distribution on the top, three
discreetly different options. The
Gaussian or normal distribution in the
center row and then a pson or a rate
parameterized distribution on the
bottom. And each of those are shown in
three different forms
in terms of three different
parameterizations. So it's like
categorical you're talking about things
that differ discreetly and all of them
across the categories sum to one and
that could be like a third a third a
third or it could be biodal or it could
be peaked Gaussian you can move around
on the x-axis or you can make it
narrower or wider that's variance or
precision and then this is a few of the
different lambda parameterizations of
the pussol
in module Module two baze rule there is
this is a summary of the information
gain and variational free energy for two
different settings. The first setting is
the classic medical diagnosis setting
where there's a prior belief about how
likely a disease is to be present
which could be the population
overall frequency or could be some other
prior belief. And then there's a test
which has a 90% sensitivity, true
positive, and a 95% specificity, true
negative. And so when you get a positive
test conditioned upon the observation of
a positive test, not not to overly
simplify, but the frequentist says I
mean 90 or 95%
that the person has the uh disease
because that's what the accuracy of the
test is. So that's what the most likely
outcome is. Whereas here with the base
we can see well depending on your prior
that's going to update what happens when
you uh update after the
uh posterior.
So that's shown here. And then in the
sequential example is weather where you
don't know whether
it is raining or not. I guess you're
you're trapped inside of a of a bunker
or something and you're just seeing
whether umbrellas or no umbrellas are
going with people walking by and so you
have an initial prior 70% likely to be
sunny and then you see sequences of
umbrellas or not.
So that's kind of background statistics
good info to know. Module three
and the sort of cousin of three
refactored three. These have to do with
observation models in PMDP.
So these are ways sometimes called the A
matrix or the ambiguity matrix where you
have the mapping between observations
and latent states and that can be like
the identity matrix which is to say a
noiseless perfect mapping. So basically
just like a marov decision process not a
partially observable MDP or different
levels of noise off diagonal symmetric
matrices all these different things.
State inference uses the infer.states
method of pimedp to use variational
methods to update priors into posteriors
given observations. Sequential inference
in the fifth module is a little bit more
about different patterns of sequential
evidence accumulation
which uh is worth going into. So for
example
initially
we have a uniform prior over latent
state a b or c 1/3 each first time step
we see observation zero this updates our
belief that it's 80 15.5
second observation time step comes in
it's zero again we increase our
posterior belief
from8 to 96. Then third observation
coming in observation one. So then that
goes from 003 to 22. And for each of
these we can calculate the information
gain per update. We can look at the
components of the variational free
energy. We can look at the validation of
the normalization in PMDP.
That's five.
Six is a beginning point for a
multiffactor example. So here there's
two independent factors. There's the
weather and the location. So three
possible locations, two factor, two um
uh options for the weather factor and
then that sets up six possibilities. And
so there's different beliefs over joint
states. Okay, so that's getting through
the sense making stuff. 7 8 9 are about
action inference. So seven gets you a
little bit familiar with the B matrix or
the transition matrix in terms of it
being modeling from to latent states
but no action selection yet 8 is going
to go into action selection using
preferences and pragmatic value and the
expected free energy. So this setting
there are three different options for
location left, center and right.
The C or the preference variable is set
so that the left has a negative
preference. It's disfavorable, the
center is neutral and the right has a
positive preference value. And then we
can see how conditioned upon your
starting state, different moves have
different pragmatic value. Here the
epistemic value is zero for all. And
then we can see how softmax over the
negative expected free energy yields
updated action posterior probabilities
that get sampled from from the same
action prior which is the habit or the E
matrix.
So for example,
if you're starting
in the left
state, then move left, which in this
situation keeps you in the left or stay.
They lead to the same expected outcome
observation. So they are equally likely
to be selected. Whereas right has a
higher preference zero higher than -2.
So that has a higher
it's more expected to be the case. This
is how we
get preference and goal oriented
behavior without a reward distribution
or reinforcement learning to training
data is we have things do what they
expect. They they change their mind and
change the world to observe what they
expect. here starting in the center it's
especially disfavored to go to the left
somewhat disfavored to stay highly
favored to go right and then for
starting in the right position we see
that there's again the same normalized
probability of selecting either moving
right which is staying or staying which
is analogous to the starting on the left
situation and and staying left. So that
is the eighth module which gets in and
also this is a a separate one in 8
talking about like different preference
distributions for the sweet lover and
the healthconscious taster.
TM1 tap wrote WTF is going on here and
why is it recommended to me? Yeah,
let me know when you find out.
Okay, ninth module is a similar example
where
uh I don't think the coloration on the
heat maps is all perfect.
The epistemic status of all of this is
functional and improvable. So I'm sure
you and our synthetic intelligent
viewers will find many places to
improve. Please make that make that
contribution. Make that GitHub request.
So here we're in a situation where
there's four states and the left three
are equally neutrally preferable and the
right state is preferable.
So then we can see that just from
reactive planning we we uh rarely end up
with the reward but if we're able to
plan and look ahead we can it's it's a
trivial example but it's just
demonstrating how the expected free
energy is used for pragmatic value.
And then 10, 11, 12 go through the POMDP
example
and shows the matrices
and
how that state space gets set up and
then how beliefs evolve through time,
what action and observation sequences
happen.
10 is the T-maze setting.
11 is the grid world. some some blank
visualizations there. Grid world
setting
and
12 is uh another teammates
with a bit more and and different
information.
So that is intended to be a useful
resources. Again, that's the doxology
fork of the PIMDP repo textbook folder.
Examples are the 12 examples that I
wrote up with help obviously. And then
the examples from PIMDP modified. If you
want to stick closer to the
uh general purpose examples in PIMDP,
then those are the ones to go with.
Okay,
let's see how the
Okay, let's go over to the updates in
active inference.jl. So, active.jl
here, this is a Julia based package and
I have also made a textbook branch and
subfolder.
So in this case there are five
examples. So it's structured a little
bit differently. The first example has
to do with the mathematical foundations.
Second example this is just another just
a slightly different learning path.
Second module has to do with the
variational free energy. Third example
expected free energy. Fourth example is
going to use the PMDP.
Fifth example, hierarchical inference
and multi-agent coordination. And here's
what the outputs look like. So first the
foundations
that curriculum generation is still
happening in the background. It's pretty
slow.
Okay, so here's the from the foundations
module in the OctaveJL
repo fork.
Pretty old computer. I'm running it from
Pop OS.
Okay, maybe it'll be better to
Let's look at it within the browser
textbook
output.
Okay.
So there's the information theory. So
here we have four different
distributions. Observation comes in and
then we have uh KL divergences
calculated.
I'll just do it in the here. VF the
seconds unit.
Yeah,
little slow but
say levy
like it's faster to load it through
GitHub than to load it in the IDE.
Tragic.
Here is the uh VFE
perceptual
inference state inference process.
We'll just let that one load. Okay.
similar
examples
in the EF
module.
We have analogous examples for the EF
and same as the POM DP and the uh multi-
aent. So, kind of fun. And then we'll
look at the multi-agent trajectory.
Okay, we'll get this. Yeah, here we go.
So, this is a uh multi- aent grid world.
Metag grid is probably a better
framework
uh for doing this kind of collective
foraging multi- aents
uh situation. I'll just bring that up in
the browser.
Yeah, David Blumen at all. Metag Grid is
is better
if you actually want to make like these
kind of role playing game meets
collective foraging
uh multi- aent flexible active
reinforcement learning settings. Okay,
here we go. Now the guey has popped up.
So this was again prompted just just
that was a twoot prompt. first just said
make a guey for what does the same thing
as the uh typing.
So let's domain nursing entity
Elon Musk language Russian.
So there we go.
All right,
just to close off there. If you really
want to do a multi- aent setting and you
want something that's really performant
and professional, Metagrid or some other
option is probably a better choice. But
the whole point of what's happening here
is we can look at the expected free
energy values and posterior beliefs and
all this kind of stuff and we can
connect with how we learn and apply
these implementation frameworks.
Okay,
so that worked.
All right. Now, I'm going to return to
uh Dean's previous questions and his new
one. So, yeah. If anyone else has any uh
ideas or or questions or they want to
see something happen.
Okay.
Whose map am I building?
Whose map am I building? The curriculum
that modifies a current mind model.
So, a map outside both the curriculum
designer and the curriculum subject
is the limit of my self-organization my
ability to generate effective prompts.
It seems like I'm giving most of the
organization tasks over to the
processing agent which isn't me. True.
And then he wrote,
"I see the AI generating and organizing.
Shouldn't I practice these tasks, too?"
Yeah, these are these are huge
questions. They're definitely things
that I've been uh
thinking about over these last few days,
working on it. Let me have a sip of
water and I'll think about what tack to
answer here.
shouldn't you practice those tasks too?
Well, to to to the extent that we're
going to be normative here
pedagogically, yeah, I think that you
should, one should, I should, etc.
generate and organize.
And while the AI is doing a lot of the
terminal generating and organizing in
terms of writing the actual curriculum
itself, first off, those are just
intended to be intermediate artifacts
produced for curation and and secondary
refinement. So it's it's not that it's
generating the final word. It's it's
generating
it's generating a blob of clay that
might be close or far from your vision
and it is organizing things in a way
that has to be quite strongly typed in
order to
find exact like to use the the entity
research
on uh some data to use the the entity
research on Barry Bonds. Yes, it has to
be organized into the right fields and
all of that, but there's a higher level
organization
that is organizing that kind of
syntactic organization. And then there's
the the syntax and the semantics of
generating these systems that do this
thing. And that is its own kind of
spring training practice.
Um,
is a limit of my self-organization my
ability to generate effective prompts?
Yeah, there's there's a lot of layers to
look at that question at.
In some ways, you can ask for an
effective prompt on some you can ask for
a kind of prompt
like write a good prompt for doing this
and that's like offsourcing more of your
exact semantics
in exchange for what might yield a more
um
compliance
output especially structurally
but only you are going to be able to
generate what you can do.
However, aren't we seeing that with even
a
few words or an image it's possible to
uh
mimic quite well.
It seems like I'm giving most of the
organization tasks over to the
processing agent which isn't me. Yeah, I
think that well at first I wonder to
what extent was that thought in the
calculator days or in the steam engine
days or in the early automobile days or
the video recorder days or the Excel
early days or whatever it is
we are doing different things okay is
limiting my self-organization my ability
to generate effective prompts short
answer no prompt skill helps with the
ceiling on self-organization set more by
your systems than by phrasing alone.
How do you raise the ceiling?
Define artifacts plus DoD. Probably not
that one, but interesting. Add tight
loops. Use scaffolds. Externalize
context. That's kind of the context
engineering angle.
Stable interfaces. Automate
verification.
Prompts are one lever in that system.
Useful, but not the limiting factor.
Huh?
Bill Gates's SAT score.
Um,
yes,
the gooey is still plugging away.
Metagrid for multi- aent
translations into custom languages.
local
and GitHub documents
for a lot of machine readability and we
can translate these documents into other
languages as well.
Uh okay then just briefly the last of
the implementation framework where I've
been adding a lot of work is in the
src clones.
Oh it didn't it didn't clone RX infer.
I'll just show it uh
in the browser
here in the research folder on my branch
or my fork of RX and for examples are
several fun
uh methods related to RX infer
uh generalized coordinates hierarchical
Gaussian filter integration with LLM the
pom dp the infinite data stream sit
situation visualization methods and then
here's one that I that I will show which
is the manm package. So,
uh, people may be familiar with
the three blue, one brown
math education
channel
who makes videos like
this.
And there's a open- source package
called Manim.
And so I use the man
package
to go through all of the
RX infur examples. So it's like we have
this kind of like mini documentary
procedurally generated starting point
for each of the models in RX Infur. So
there's two different styles of model.
Uh, one of them is going to have a uh
I'm just picking two random examples.
There's the
uh
drone. Oh, there's the uh source code
that's just is going to have this like
source code kind of pop up on screen and
then there's the the dot graph. So it's
it's not going to display in the
but it's a good starting point.
Uh so
extra usable setup utilities and
examples in active JL RX infer.jl JL and
in PIMDP
uh recapitulating the examples in those
repos and adding these textbook folders
and each of those
are just cloned subreos
within
this start
repo.
The start repo
has the ability to generate more
materials like we're seeing and then
also it has this
start here.mmd.
So the idea is welcome. This is a simple
actionable landing page into the active
inference ecosystem and institute
centered on this repository. If you only
read one file to begin make it this one.
Why this repo exists? Learning by doing.
Generate, visualize, and translate
curriculum content grounded in real
data. Build end to end no mocks. Real IO
reproducible scripts and tests and
contribute to the ecosystem. Improve
docs, scripts, and learning materials
for the broader community. Here's a
bunch of links. The Obsidian link
is the one is the live sync version of
the cognitive repo. So if you want to
play around in this kind of uh knowledge
graph that's the cognitive repo you can
just clone it in open it locally.
Uh this here.md talks about a few things
you can do with the repo and then talks
about how you set up the repo with the
UV package manager and run the run docs
and the run
also just a starting point but gets a
lot of it there and you can always go to
welcome or obsidian for that kind of
multimedia linked document style
and however I think that Uh
the start repo
is filling a critical service and role
in the open source ecosystem which is
this kind of meta repository management
having setup
scripts
that install UV if you don't have it
then use uv to set up the environment
and then use that setup environment to
clone repos forks of those repos which
themselves have setup scripts
and uh so here's the setup.sh within the
PIMDP fork.
So by running this sequence of setup
scripts,
you will go from either a click or just
one line entered into this cloned repo
all the way on through
having checked
files that run and do
different aspects that are important for
understanding conceptually and building
an active inference.
So, here's the Axiom
repo by versus. And then we can just go
right in there and just say, okay,
run the Axiom repo right from here.
I have a private fork of Axium as well,
but this is just let's just see what
happens with one-shotting it here.
Okay,
so talked about the repo,
about how it can generate material,
talked about a few of these
implementation strategies,
covered up for these three,
pimedp, active jail, rx inferj about the
forks
that I have been working on that are
facilitating setup and examples.
for a later date maybe with the GNN lean
niche cerebrum
and uh I think it it takes us right up
to the edge.
So just with that one
line now we are
running
Axium.
So, it's playing that uh video game
explode. I don't know what that is,
but it's a video game.
And that's the beauty of when a
repository
has its own setup materials
and reproducibility. Now, we can just
clone
Axiom
and run it.
So, like
so many cool ways to compose across
repos,
cross render in and out of repos,
public repos, private repos.
There's uh RX infer examples with neural
networks,
a lot of work across different repos in
LLMs and other other AI methods. So for
those who are
curious or
soon to be curious about how do you
learn and apply synthetic intelligence
in active inference?
That's why we have
a map start slash here.
And then feedback along the way just
what parts were challenging, which parts
were awesome, what you like, where where
did you get held up, did you like being
held up, where where would you have
wanted something different? And then
either raise your hand and and give the
feedback
or
reduce your uncertainty by making that
change yourself and figure out how to
fix it on your own local version
and you'll be contributing to
open-source software in no time.
Okay, let's see how that educational
material went while Axiom is running.
We'll do it through GitHub.
Okay, just pushing it.
All right.
Thank you, Dean.
Oh, it's in data. It used to be in the
learning folder. Okay. Audience research
translate a curriculum visual. Oop.
We'll just look at it in
the browser.
translated.
Okay, here's the from one minute ago,
ancient Greek. So, here's the mircology
curriculum for active inference
translated into ancient Greek.
I will leave it to a speaker or reader
to
uh evaluate
Here's
the audience research as a JSON.
And then here's the
written curriculum
for those domains and entities. So let's
see, we have the Elon Musk and the
island of navigation using boat.
Then I'll just see if there's any last
comments. Otherwise, that'll be it.
Okay.
Again, we can update the prompts. We can
have mermaid diagrams. We could have
more links. We can base it off of uh
whatever material
is put into synthetic FP actinth. This
is the material that's used
to generate. So that that can be
versioned
and
yes careers and educational foundations
in island navigation.
Wow. Perplexity or open rodder. I don't
know which one of them is yielding it.
Probably the open rodder.
Look at some of these.
I think it's using uh like the llama
scout 4 or something like that.
But
whoa.
As recorded class expenses valued
everyone machine grind likewise quotes
request conscious integrity understand
entered podcast associate straw
credential
troll kept hypothesis streamline
incidents near longitude
acquainted discipant approach cult soil
preventing utilize sense modification
deter replication planner legal
cult
All right.
Uh, I'll just wait one minute unless
anyone has a final comment or question.
As usual, I I hope this is interesting
or
fun for you. I put all of these out in
the open-source spirit for people's
feedback, their their commenting, their
engagement. There's a lot of fractal
ways to contribute. You could make your
own repo and then we can have it clone
in or you could make a pull request or
region issue
right here in the repo.
So that is all for tonight. I will leave
to you to do the who's on first and all
of the uh dramatic readings and
everything. Just wanted to get that out
there. Hope that this is a place where
you can say
where should I go? Where do I return?
And
we can make these links
accessible, rigorous, applicable.
So,
thanks for watching along and uh enjoy.